Patrick McTaggart-Cowan fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
- Photographs, 1930 - 1985; F-65-7; 19 cm of textual records ca. 350 photographs
  - General photographs, 1938 - 1979; F-65-7-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 65-21)
  - Photographs - Oxford, 1936; F-65-7-0-0-22 (Archival box - small 65-29)
  - Official opening of the Gaglardi Highway, 1965; F-65-7-0-0-23 (Archival box - small 65-29)
  - North Atlantic Route Service Conference photo (oversize), 1946; F-65-7-0-0-24
  - Corpus Christi College Freshmen, Oxford (oversize), 1934; F-65-7-0-0-25
  - Negatives: Lord Lovat, SFU construction, [ca 1965]; F-65-7-0-0-26 (Archival box - small 65-29)
    Photographic materials
- Artifacts, [19--?] - 1992; F-65-8; 17 artifacts
  Series consists of a collection of artifacts accumulated by Patrick McTaggart-Cowan. Includes trophies, plaques, one print, and medals received by McTaggart-Cowan including the Order of Canada and Member of the British Empire. Series also includes a wooden replica of the university mace presented to McTaggart-Cowan in 1968.
  - Joint Canadian-U.S. Arctic Weather Stations plaque, 1971; F-65-8-0-0-0-1 (Artifact box - large 65-33)
    Artefacts
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item1.
  - Ontario Agricultural College plaque, 1974; F-65-8-0-0-0-2 (Artifact box - large 65-33)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item2.
  - Canadian Meteorology plaque, 1971; F-65-8-0-0-0-3 (Artifact box - large 65-33)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item3.
  - "First Shrum Bowl", 1967; F-65-8-0-0-0-4 (Artifact box - large 65-30)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-8-0-2, F-65-item4.
  - Athletic Support (Football) Trophy, 1965 - 1966; F-65-8-0-0-0-5 (Artifact box - large 65-30)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-8-0-2, F-65-item5.
  - Paper-weight inscribed "In Appreciation of Your Contribution to Education for the Computer Age", 1967; F-65-8-0-0-0-6 (Artifact box - large 65-30)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-8-0-2, F-65-item6.
  - Plaque "Honorary Membership: SFU Science Undergraduate Society", 1966; F-65-8-0-0-0-7 (Artifact box - large 65-30)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-8-0-2, F-65-item7.
  - Framed letters "Honourary Member - Varsity Letterman's Club", 1967; F-65-8-0-0-0-8 (Artifact box - large 65-31)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-8-0-2, F-65-item8.
  - Framed print - Simon Fraser's house at St. Ausse de Bellevue, [19--?]; F-65-8-0-0-0-9 (Artifact box - large 65-31)
    Graphic materials
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item9.
  - Order of Canada medal, 1979; F-65-8-0-0-0-10 (Artifact box - small 65-32)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item10.
  - Member of British Empire medal, [19--]; F-65-8-0-0-0-11 (Artifact box - small 65-32)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item11.
  - Canada Confederation medal, 1967; F-65-8-0-0-0-12 (Artifact box - small 65-32)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item12.
  - The Patterson Medal for Distinguished Service to Meteorology, 1964; F-65-8-0-0-0-13 (Artifact box - small 65-32)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item13.
  - Queen Elizabeth II Coronation medal, 1953; F-65-8-0-0-0-14 (Artifact box - small 65-32)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item14.
  - Canadian 1867-1992 Confederation medal, F-65-8-0-0-0-15 (Artifact box - small 65-32)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item15.
  - The Miracle Mile medal, 1967; F-65-8-0-0-0-16 (Artifact box - small 65-32)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item16.
  - Replica university mace on wooden display stand, 1968; F-65-8-0-0-0-17 (Artifact box - small 65-32)
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-65-item17.
- Chedabucto Bay (N.S.) oil spill clean-up (Operation Oil) records, 1970 - 1974; F-65-9; 75 cm of textual records
  Series comprises records relating to McTaggart-Cowan's work as Head of the Task Force Operation Oil, established by the Minister of Transport in February 1970.
  On February 4, 1970 the Liberian tanker the Arrow was wrecked on Cerberus Rock in Chedabucto Bay, off Cape Breton Island, Nova Scotia. The tanker was bound from Venezuela carrying a cargo of 108,000 barrels of Bunker C fuel oil for Imperial Oil Limited. It is estimated that some two-thirds of the cargo was released into the Bay, polluting 190 miles of the Bay's 375-mile shoreline. The wreck in Chedabucto Bay was the first major spill of heavy Bunker C oil in frigid waters and presented problems for clean-up which were without precedent.
  Initial clean-up efforts were directed by James Hornsby of Imperial Oil; he was replaced on February 13. On February 20, the Minster of Tranport appointed a three-man Task Force dubbed “Operation Oil,” with McTaggart-Cowan as the Head, assisted by Dr. H. Sheffer of the Defense Research Board of Canada (Deputy Head), and Capt. M. A. Martin of Maritime Command. The mandate of the Task Force was to minimize damage to the economy and ecology of the region, to gain a knowledge and understanding of oil spills in order to contend with similar incidents in the future, and to make recommendations for minimizing occurrences of oil spills and for providing immediate response and control. In overseeing the clean-up, the Task Force established various headquarters and field units, with much of the on-site capability being provided by the Canadian Armed Forces. Operation Oil reported to the Minister on September 1, 1970 (Final Report, volumes I - III). Clean-up efforts continued over the next two years, and the Task Force delivered the fourth and last volume of its Final Report on May 23, 1972.
  Records include correspondence, memoranda, minutes, photographs, diaries, reports and publications (including the Final Report of the Task Force), press releases and press clippings, telegrams, proposals, contracts, plans and drawings, claims sheets and invoices.
  Note that the records in this series were made or received by McTaggart-Cowan in his official capacity as Head of the Task Force, an agency of the federal government. Accordingly, in terms of provenance these are public records of Ministry of Transport. The records remained, however, in the physical custody of McTaggart-Cowan and were transferred to the Archives along with his private papers.
  Note that associated records may also be held by the federal government department Environment Canada. According to a letter to McTaggart-Cowan dated July 6, 1971 (see file F-65-9-1-19), "much of the reconnaissance data obtained at Chedabucto Bay on ‘Operation Oil' has been placed on microfilm and is stored at the Canadian Oceanographic Data Centre."
  - Operation Oil correspondence and working files, 1970 - 1974; F-65-9-1; 41 cm of textual records
    Subseries comprises records relating to the activities of Operation Oil, including project management, liaison with the Ministry of Transport, salvage, clean-up, research, international correspondence, and liaison with the local community and general public.
    Records consist predominantly of correspondence and memoranda, but also include McTaggart-Cowan's operations diaries, telegrams, reports, proposals, plans, drawings, press releases, claims sheets, and invoices.
    - Background documents, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 65-22)
      Pending review
    - Claims, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 65-22)
    - Claims, 1971; F-65-9-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 65-22)
    - Claims, 1972 - 1974; F-65-9-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 65-22)
    - Complaints, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 65-22)
    - Correspondence - H.J.A. Neu, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 65-22)
    - Correspondence - Minister of Transportation, 1970 - 1971; F-65-9-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 65-22)
    - Correspondence - General Public, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 65-22)
    - Correspondence - General Public, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 65-23)
    - Correspondence - General Public, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 65-23)
    - Correspondence - General Public, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 65-23)
    - Correspondence - Regulations, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 65-23)
    - Correspondence - Shipping and Pollution, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 65-23)
    - Correspondence and memoranda - General, 1970 - 1973; F-65-9-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 65-23)
    - Correspondence and memoranda - General, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 65-23)
    - Correspondence and memoranda - General, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 65-23)
    - Correspondence and memoranda - General, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Correspondence and memoranda - General, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Correspondence and memoranda - General, 1970 - 1971; F-65-9-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Inquiries - Foreign, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-20 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Inspection, 1972; F-65-9-1-0-21 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Judicial inquiry, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-22 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Lennox Passage and CanscoTickle Plans, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-23 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Operation Oil diaries, 1970; F-65-9-1-0-24 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Operation Oil participants, F-65-9-1-0-25 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Operation re-pump, 1970 - 1971; F-65-9-1-0-26 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Operations follow-up, 1971; F-65-9-1-0-27 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Research - Biodegradation, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-28 (Archival box - standard 65-24)
    - Research - General, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-29 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Research - oil finger printing, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-1-0-30 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Salvage, 1970 - 1970; F-65-9-1-0-31 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Art (artist unknown), F-65-9-1-0-32 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
  - Operation Oil minutes, 1970; F-65-9-2; 4 cm of textual records
    Subseries comprises records relating to the regular meetings of Operation Oil personnel, including meetings of Task Force heads and meetings of the evening staff. Records consist of minutes.
    - Operation Oil meetings, 1970; F-65-9-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Operation Oil meetings, 1970; F-65-9-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Operation Oil meetings, 1970; F-65-9-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Operation Oil meetings, 1970; F-65-9-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Evening Staff meetings, 1970; F-65-9-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
  - Operation Oil photographs, 1970; F-65-9-3; 4 cm of textual records ca. 75 photographs
    Subseries comprises photographic records documenting the activities of Operation Oil. Records consist of photographs, a register of negatives and correspondence with the photographer.
    - Negatives log - Operation Oil, 1970; F-65-9-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Marine services photographs, 1970; F-65-9-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Photographs, 1970; F-65-9-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Photographs O-001 - O-195, 1970; F-65-9-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Photographs O-203 - O-435, 1970; F-65-9-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
  - Operation Oil reports, 1970 - 1973; F-65-9-4; 17 cm of textual records
    Subseries comprises records relating to the communication of the activities and findings of Operation Oil. Records consist of reports received by McTaggart-Cowan from the various units of the Task Force, situation reports and progress reports sent to Ottawa by McTaggart-Cowan, and Operation Oil's published Final Report. Volumes I – III of the Final Report were submitted to the Minister in 1970; Volume IV covered the subsequent follow-up activities and was delivered in 1972 (published 1973).
    - Situation reports to Ottawa, 1970; F-65-9-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Situation reports to Ottawa, 1970; F-65-9-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Progress reports, 1970 - 1971; F-65-9-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports - beach cleaning, 1970; F-65-9-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports, 1970 - 1970; F-65-9-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports, 1970 - 1970; F-65-9-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports, 1970 - 1970; F-65-9-4-0-7 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports, 1970; F-65-9-4-0-8 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports, 1970; F-65-9-4-0-9 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports, 1970; F-65-9-4-0-10 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports, 1970 - 1970; F-65-9-4-0-11 (Archival box - standard 65-26)
    - Reports, 1971; F-65-9-4-0-12 (Archival box - standard 65-27)
    - Final Report of the Task Force Operation Oil Vol. 1-III, 1970; F-65-9-4-0-13 (Archival box - standard 65-27)
    - Final Report of the Task Force Operation Oil Vol. IV, 1973; F-65-9-4-0-14 (Archival box - standard 65-27)
  - Publications and presentations, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-5; 2 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of articles, presentations and correspondence relating to public speaking engagements by McTaggart-Cowan concerning his experiences, findings and opinions relating to the Chedabucto Bay oil spill.
    - Articles and presentations, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
    - Speaking engagements, 1970; F-65-9-5-0-2 (Archival box - standard 65-25)
  - Related reference material, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-6; 8 cm of textual records
    Subseries comprises documents relating to the Chedabucto Bay oil spill which were received or collected by McTaggart-Cowan and retained for background, reference and information purposes. The authors of the material were not members of the Task Force and include academics, government and industry researchers, and journalists. Records consist of press clippings and published and non-published studies, reports and papers.
    - Bibliography, 1972; F-65-9-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 65-27)
    - Reports and publications, 1970 - 1970; F-65-9-6-0-2 (Archival box - standard 65-27)
    - Reports and publications, 1970 - 1970; F-65-9-6-0-3 (Archival box - standard 65-27)
    - Reports and publications, 1972; F-65-9-6-0-4 (Archival box - standard 65-27)
    - Royal Commission on Steam Tanker "Arrow" - Final report, 1971; F-65-9-6-0-5 (Archival box - standard 65-27)
    - Press clippings, 1970 - 1972; F-65-9-6-0-6 (Archival box - standard 65-27)